(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you for being here.
شكرا لوجودكم هنا.
And I say "thank you for being here" because I was silent for 17 years.
و أنا أقول شكرا لوجودكم هنا، لأنني لزمت الصَّمت لمدة 17 سنة.
And the first words that I spoke were in Washington, D.C.,
وكانت العاصمة واشنطن هي المكان الذي تفوّهت فيه بأول كلمات.
on the 20th anniversary of Earth Day.
في الذّكرى العشرون ليوم الأرض.
And my family and friends had gathered there to hear me speak.
و قد تجمّع هنالك أهلي و أصدقائي لسَمَاعِي أتحدّث.
And I said, "Thank you for being here."
و قد قلت ،"شكرا لوجودكم هنا."
My mother, out in the audience, she jumped up,
أمي، التي كانت من بين المستمعين، قفزت،
"Hallelujah, Johnny’s talking!"
"الحمد لله ، جوني يتكلم!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Imagine if you were quiet for 17 years
تخيل أنك التزمت الصمت طوال 17 سنة
and your mother was out in the audience, say.
وكانت والدتك من بين المستمعين.
My dad said to me, "That’s one" --
والدي قال لي، "هذه هي" --
I’ll explain that.
سأفسّر ذلك لاحقا.
But I turned around because I didn’t recognize where my voice was coming from.
لكنني التفت حولي لأنني لم أستطع التعرف على مصدر صوتي.
I hadn’t heard my voice in 17 years,
لم أسمع صوتي منذ 17 سنة،
so I turned around and I looked and I said,
لذلك التفت حولي و نظرت ثم قلت،
"God, who's saying what I’m thinking?"
"يا إلهي، من ذا الذي ينطق بما أنا بصدد التفكير فيه؟"
And then I realized it was me, you know, and I kind of laughed.
ثم أدركت أنه أنا، تعلمون، جعلني ذلك أضحك قليلا.
And I could see my father: "Yeah, he really is crazy."
كنت أستطيع أن ألمح والدي يقول -- "نعم ، انه حقا مجنون "
Well, I want to take you on this journey.
حسن، أود أن أصطحبكم إلى هذه الرحلة.
And the journey, I believe, is a metaphor for all of our journeys.
وأعتقد أن هذه الرحلة هي استعارة لكل رحلاتنا.
Even though this one is kind of unusual,
و لذلك، حتى وإن كانت غير عادية،
I want you to think about your own journey.
أريدكم ان تفكروا في رحلاتكم أنتم.
My journey began in 1971
بدأت رحلتي في سنة 1971
when I witnessed two oil tankers collide beneath the Golden Gate,
يومها شهدت إصطدام ناقلتي نفط تحت جسر "جولدن جايت"
and a half a million gallons of oil spilled into the bay.
وإنسكب نصف مليون جالون من النفط في الخليج.
It disturbed me so much
لقد أزعجني ذلك أيما إزعاج
that I decided that I was going to give up riding and driving in motorized vehicles.
إلى درجة أنني قررت أنني سوف أتوقف عن ركوب و قيادة المركبات الآلية.
That’s a big thing in California.
وهو امرٌ صعب في كاليفورنيا.
And it was a big thing in my little community of Point Reyes Station
وخاصة في منطقتي في "بوينت رايز ستايشن"
in Inverness, California, because there were only
في "أيفرنيس"، "كاليفورنيا"، لأنه كان يقطنها
about 350 people there in the winter – this was back in '71 now.
شتاءا حوالي 350 شخصا فقط - يعود هذا إلى سنة 71.
And so when I came in and I started walking around, people --
و عندما مضيت قُدُمًا و بدأت بالتجوال مشيا، بدأ الناس --
they just knew what was going on.
كانوا حديثي عهد بما يحدث.
And people would drive up next to me
كان الناس يقودون سياراتهم بقربي
and say, "John, what are you doing?"
و يقولون،"جون، ماذا تفعل؟"
And I’d say, "Well, I’m walking for the environment."
كنت أجيبهم،" أنا أسير من أجل الحفاظ على البيئة."
And they said, "No, you’re walking to make us look bad, right?
فكانوا يقولون،" لا، أنت تسير لتجعلنا نظهر بمظهر سيّء، أليس كذلك؟
You’re walking to make us feel bad."
أنت تسير لتجعلنا نحس بإمتعاض."
And maybe there was some truth to that,
ربما كان فيما يقولون شيء من الحقيقة،
because I thought that if I started walking, everyone would follow.
لأنني كنت أعتقد أنني إذا بدأت في المشي سيتبعني الجميع في ذلك.
Because of the oil, everybody talked about the polllution.
بسبب النفط، يتحدث الجميع عن التلوث.
And so I argued with people about that, I argued and I argued.
و لذلك فقد كنت أتجادل مع الناس حول ذلك، باستمرار.
I called my parents up.
دعوت والديّ.
I said, "I’ve given up riding and driving in cars."
وقلت،" لقد توقفت عن ركوب و قيادة السّيارات."
My dad said, "Why didn’t you do that when you were 16?"
قال والدي،"لم لم تفعل ذلك عندما كان عمرك 16 سنة؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I didn’t know about the environment then.
عندها لم أكن أعلم الكثير عن البيئة.
They’re back in Philadelphia.
عادوا إلى "فيلادلفيا".
And so I told my mother, "I’m happy though, I’m really happy."
فقلت لأمي،" أنا مع ذلك سعيد، أنا حقا سعيد."
She said, "If you were happy, son, you wouldn’t have to say it."
فقالت،" إذا كنت سعيدا، إبني، فلا يتعين عليك أن تبوح بذلك."
Mothers are like that.
الأمهات هنّ هكذا.
And so, on my 27th birthday I decided, because I argued so much
في يوم احتفالي بعيد ميلادي الـسابع و العشرين، و لأني كنت كثير الجدال
and I talk so much, that I was going to stop speaking
و كثير الكلام، كما ترون، قررت أن أتوقف عن الكلام
for just one day -- one day -- to give it a rest.
ليوم واحد -- يوم واحد -- لآخذ فترة راحة.
And so I did.
وذلك ما فعلت.
I got up in the morning and I didn’t say a word.
نهضت عند الصباح و لم أهمس ببنت شفة.
And I have to tell you, it was a very moving experience,
وعلي أن أخبركم ، أنّ تلك التجربة جعلتني أتغير،
because for the first time, I began listening -- in a long time.
لأنني بدأت ولأول مرة، بالإستماع -- و لفترة طويلة.
And what I heard, it kind of disturbed me.
وقد أزعجني ما سمعته.
Because what I used to do, when I thought I was listening,
لأنّني عندما كنت أعتقد أنّني بصدد الإستماع، ما كنت في الواقع أقوم به
was I would listen just enough to hear what people had to say
كان الإستماع قليلا لما يقوله الآخرون
and think that I could -- I knew what they were going to say,
والإعتقاد أنه بإمكاني -- أنّني أعلم مالذي سوف يقولونه،
and so I stopped listening.
ولذا كنت أتوقف عن الإستماع.
And in my mind, I just kind of raced ahead
و في ذهني، كنت أستبق
and thought of what I was going to say back,
وأفكر في الجواب الذي سأقوله،
while they were still finishing up.
بينما كانوا بصدد إنهاء حديثهم.
And then I would launch in.
و من ثم كنت أسترسل.
Well, that just ended communication.
حسن، قمت بقطع التواصل.
So on this first day I actually listened.
لذا قمت في ذلك اليوم الأول بالإستماع.
And it was very sad for me,
و كان ذلك أمرا محزنا بالنسبة لي،
because I realized that for those many years I had not been learning.
لأنّني أدركت أنّني وطوال تلك السنوات العديدة لم أتعّلم.
I was 27. I thought I knew everything.
كنت في السابعة و العشرين من عمري. كنت اعتقد أنني أعلم كل شيء.
I didn’t.
لم يكن ذلك صحيحا.
And so I decided I’d better do this for another day,
ولذلك قرّرت أن أقوم بذلك ليوم آخر،
and another day, and another day until finally,
فيوما آخر، فيوما آخر حتى إنتهى بي الأمر،
I promised myself for a year I would keep quiet
لأن أعاهد نفسي على الصمت سنة كاملة
because I started learning more and more and I needed to learn more.
لأنّني بدأت بالتعلّم أكثر فأكثر و كنت بحاجة لأن أتعلم أكثر.
So for a year I said I would keep quiet,
لذا قررت أن ألزم الصمت طوال سنة.
and then on my birthday I would reassess what I had learned
و عند حلول عيد ميلادي سوف أقوم بمراجعة ما تمكّنت من تعلمه
and maybe I would talk again.
وربما سأعاود الحديث مجددا.
Well, that lasted 17 years.
حسنا ، لقد استمر ذلك 17 عاما.
Now during that time -- those 17 years -- I walked and I played the banjo
أمضيت تلك الفترة - تلك السبعة عشر عاما - في المشي و العزف على آلة البانجو
and I painted and I wrote in my journal, and
والرسم و كتابة مذكراتي
I tried to study the environment by reading books.
وكنت أحاول دراسة البيئة عن طريق المطالعة.
And I decided that I was going to go to school. So I did.
ومن ثم قررت أنه عليّ الذهاب إلى المدرسة. وهكذا فعلت.
I walked up to Ashland, Oregon,
انطلقت مشيا إلى "اشلاند"، "أوريغون"،
where they were offering an environmental studies degree.
أين كان بالإمكان الحصول على شهادة الدراسات البيئية.
It’s only 500 miles.
كانت تبعد مسافة 500 ميل فقط.
And I went into the Registrar’s office and --
ذهبت إلى مكتب التسجيل و...
"What, what, what?"
ماذا، ماذا تقول؟
I had a newspaper clipping.
كانت بحوزتي قصاصة من جريدة.
"Oh, so you really want to go to school here?
أوه ، أحقا تريد ارتياد المدرسة هنا؟
You don’t …?
ليس لديك ... ؟
We have a special program for you." They did.
لدينا برنامج خاص لك. و هكذا فعلوا.
And in those two years, I graduated with my first degree -- a bachelor’s degree.
وخلال تلك السنتين، تحصلت على شهادتي الجامعية الأولى -- درجة البكالوريوس.
And my father came out, he was so proud.
حضر أبي و كان فخورا جدا بذلك.
He said, "Listen, we’re really proud of you son,
ثم قال،" اسمع يا ولدي، نحن حقا فخورون بك
but what are you going to do with a bachelor’s degree?
ولكن ما الذي يمكن أن تفعله بشهادة البكالوريوس
You don’t ride in cars, you don’t talk --
أنت لا تركب السيارات، لا تتكلّم،
you’re going to have to do those things."
سوف يكون عليك القيام بهذين الأمرين."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I hunched my shoulder, I picked my backpack up again
أومأت بكتفي، ثم حملت حقيبتي مجددا
and I started walking.
وبدأت المشي.
I walked all the way up to Port Townsend, Washington, where I built a wooden boat,
مشيت على طول الطريق حتى ميناء "تاونسند" ، "واشنطن" ، حيث قمت ببناء قارب خشبي،
rode it across Puget Sound
قدته حتّى "بوجيه ساوند".
and walked across Washington [to] Idaho and down to Missoula, Montana.
"اداهو" -- مررت عبر "واشنطن"، "أيداهو" ونزولا إلى "ميسولا"، "مونتانا".
I had written the University of Montana two years earlier
كنت قد كتبت إلى جامعة "مونتانا" قبل عامين
and said I'd like to go to school there.
وعبرت لهم عن رغبتي في الدراسة هناك.
I said I'd be there in about two years.
أخبرتهم أني سوف أصل بعد نحو عامين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I was there. I showed up in two years and they --
ثم وصلت إلى هناك. ظهرت بعد عامين و قد قاموا --
I tell this story because they really helped me.
أنا أحكي هذه القصّة لأنّهم حقا قدّموا لي يد المساعدة.
There are two stories in Montana.
كان هناك أمران في "مونتانا".
The first story is I didn’t have any money -- that’s a sign I used a lot.
الأمر الأول هو أنه لم يكن بحوزتي مال على الإطلاق -- كثيرا ما كنت أستعمل هذه الإشارة.
And they said,"Don't worry about that."
فأجابوني،" لا تقلق بهذا الشأن."
The director of the program said, "Come back tomorrow."
ثم أردف مدير البرامج قائلا ،"عُدْ في الغد."
He gave me 150 dollars,
أعطاني مبلغ 150 دولارا،
and he said, "Register for one credit.
ثم قال،"قم بالتسجيل في مادة واحدة.
You’re going to go to South America, aren’t you?"
سوف تذهب إلى أمريكا الجنوبية، أليس كذلك؟"
And I said --
فقلت --
Rivers and lakes, the hydrological systems, South America.
أنهار و بحيرات، النظم الهيدرولوجية ، أمريكا الجنوبية.
So I did that.
فكان ذلك ما فعلت.
He came back; he said to me,
ثم عاد، و قال لي،
"OK John, now that you've registered for that one credit,
قال ،" حسن جون، الآن و بما أنك قمت بالتسجيل في مادة واحدة،
you can have a key to an office, you can matriculate --
فإنه يحق لك الحصول على مفتاح لأحد المكاتب، يمكنك التسجيل --
you’re matriculating, so you can use the library.
أنت مُسَجَّلٌ لذا يُخَوَّلُ لك استعمال المكتبة.
And what we’re going to do
وما سنقوم به
is, we’re going to have all of the professors allow you to go to class.
هو أنه سنطلب من جميع المدرسين السماح لك بمُتابعة الدروس،
They’re going to save your grade,
وسوف يقومون بحفظ درجاتك
and when we figure out how to get you the rest of the money,
و عندما نَتَدَبَّرُ أمر الحصول على المال المتبقّي،
then you can register for that class and they’ll give you the grade."
عندها يمكنك التسجيل في ذلك الصف و الحصول على الدرجة."
Wow, they don’t do that in graduate schools, I don’t think.
رائع، إنهم لا يتصرّفون هكذا في المعاهد العليا، لا أعتقد ذلك.
But I use that story because they really wanted to help me.
ولكني ذكرت هذه الحكاية لأنهم أرادوا بالفعل تقديم يد العون لي.
They saw that I was really interested in the environment,
لقد لاحظوا شدة اهتمامي بالبيئة،
and they really wanted to help me along the way.
وكانوا يريدون مساعدتي في هذا الطريق.
And during that time, I actually taught classes without speaking.
و خلال تلك الفترة، قمت بالدراسة بدون أن أتكلم.
I had 13 students when I first walked into the class.
في البداية عندما بدأت الدراسة كان معي 13 طالبا،
I explained, with a friend who could interpret my sign language,
وقد أوضحت لهم، بِمَعِيَّةِ صديق كان يستطيع فهم لغة الإشارات،
that I was John Francis, I was walking around the world,
أنني أدعى "جون فرانسيس"، و أني قمت بالمشي حول العالم،
I didn’t talk and this was the last time
و أني لم أتكلم و كان تلك آخر مرة
this person’s going to be here interpreting for me.
يقوم بها ذلك الشخص بالترجمة
All the students sat around and they went ...
جلس كل الطلبة حولي و كانوا هكذا...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I could see they were looking for the schedule,
كنت أراهم يبحثون في الجدول الدراسي
to see when they could get out.
ليعرفوا متى يستطيعون المغادرة
They had to take that class with me.
كانوا يَوَدُّونَ حضور ذلك الدرس معي.
Two weeks later, everyone was trying to get into our class.
بعد مرور أسبوعين، كان الجميع يَوَدُّونَ حضور الدرس معي.
And I learned in that class -- because I would do things like this ...
أخذت ذلك الدرس -- لأني أود القيام بأشياء مثل هذا ...
and they were all gathered around, going, "What's he trying to say?"
كانوا يتجمعون حولي ،مالذي يحاول قوله؟
"I don't know, I think he's talking about clear cutting." "Yeah, clear cutting."
لا أدري، أعتقد أنه يتحدث عن القطع التام للأشجار. أجل القطع التام للأشجار.
"No, no, no, that's not clear cutting, that’s -- he's using a handsaw."
لا، لا، لا، هذا ليس القطع التام للأشجار، هذا -- انه يستخدم المنشار.
"Well, you can’t clearcut with a ..."
حسن، لن يكون بإمكانك القيام بالقطع التام للأشجار باستخدام ...
"Yes, you can clear cut ..."
نعم، بمكانك القيام بالقطع التام للأشجار ...
"No, I think he’s talking about selective forestry."
لا، أعتقد انه يتحدث عن الغابات الإنتقائية.
Now this was a discussion class and we were having a discussion.
كان هذا نقاشا داخل الصف و كنا بصدد إجراء مناقشة.
I just backed out of that, you know, and I just kind of kept the fists from flying.
كنت أتهرّب بعض الشيء، كما تعلمون، محاولا فقط تجنب خروج الأمر عن السيطرة.
But what I learned was that sometimes I would make a sign
و لكن ما تعلمته كان هو أني كنت أقوم في بعض الأحيان بإشارة
and they said things that I absolutely did not mean,
وكانوا يفسرونها بأمور لم أكن أبدا أقصدها،
but I should have.
ولكن كان ينبغي ان تكون لديّ.
And so what came to me is, if you were a teacher
و ما خطر لي هو أنه إذا كنت مدرسا
and you were teaching, if you weren’t learning
وكنت بصدد التدريس، إذا كنت أنت نفسك لا تعلم
you probably weren’t teaching very well.
فمن المؤكد أنَّك لن تكون مُدَرِّسًا جيدا.
And so I went on.
فمضيت في ذلك.
My dad came out to see me graduate
أتى والدي ليحضر تخرجي
and, you know, I did the deal,
و، كما تعلمون، حصلت على الرهان،
and my father said, "We’re really proud of you son, but ... "
وقال لي والدي، "اسمع يا ولدي، نحن حقا فخورون بك، و لكن..."
You know what went on,
بإمكانكم أن تعرفوا مالذي حدث،
he said, "You’ve got to start riding and driving and start talking.
قال،"عليك أن تبدأ بالركوب و القيادة و أن تبدأ بالكلام.
What are you going to do with a master’s degree?"
مالذي ستفعله بدرجة الماجستير؟"
I hunched my shoulder, I got my backpack
أومأت بكتفي، ثم حملت حقيبتي مجددا
and I went on to the University of Wisconsin.
ثم التحقت بجامعة "وسكونسن".
I spent two years there writing on oil spills.
قضيت هناك سنتين أكتب عن تسرب النفط.
No one was interested in oil spills.
ولم يكن أحد مهتما بتسرب النفط.
But something happened --
ولكن شيئا ما حدث --
Exxon Valdez.
"إكسون فالديز".
And I was the only one in the United States writing on oil spills.
وكنت الوحيد في الولايات المتحدة الذي يكتب عن تسرب النفط.
My dad came out again.
أتى والدي مجددا.
He said, "I don't know how you do this, son --
قال،"بُنَيَّ، لا أدري كيف تفعل ذلك،
I mean, you don't ride in cars, you don’t talk.
أقصد، أنت لا تركب السيارات، لا تتكلم.
My sister said maybe I should leave you alone,
أختي تقول إنّه ربما من الأفضل أن أتركك وحيدا،
because you seem to be doing a lot better
لأنه يبدو أنك تتصرف بطريقة أفضل
when you’re not saying anything."
عندما تلزم الصمت."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Well, I put on my backpack again.
حسن، حملت حقيبتي مجددا.
I put my banjo on and I walked all the way to the East Coast,
أخذت آلة البانجو ومشيت كل الطريق صوب الساحل الشرقي،
put my foot in the Atlantic Ocean --
لأضع قدمي في المحيط الأطلسيّ -
it was seven years and one day it took me to walk across the United States.
تَطَلَّبَ ِمنِّي قَطْعُ الولايات المتحدة سبع سنين و يوما واحدا من المشي.
And on Earth Day, 1990 --
و في يوم الأرض، سنة 1990،
the 20th anniversary of Earth Day -- that’s when I began to speak.
وفي الذكرى العشرين ليوم الأرض بدأت في الكلام.
And that’s why I said, "Thank you for being here."
ولهذا قلت، "شكرا لوجودكم هنا."
Because it's sort of like that tree in the forest falling;
لأنّ ذلك يشبه سقوط شجرة في الغابة،
and if there's no one there to hear, does it really make a sound?
فإذا لم يكن أحد هناك ليسمع -- فهل تصدر حقا صوتا؟
And I’m thanking you, and I'm thanking my family
و أنا أشكركم، و أشكر عائلتي،
because they had come to hear me speak.
لأنها قدمت لتسمعني أتكلم.
And that’s communication.
وهذا هو التواصل.
And they also taught me about listening -- that they listened to me.
وكما علموني أيضا الإستماع -- لقد استمعوا لي.
And it’s one of those things that came out of the silence,
وهذا بعض ما ينتج عن السكوت،
the listening to each other.
استماعنا لبعضنا البعض.
Really, very important --
حقا، هذا أمر مهم --
we need to listen to each other.
علينا الإستماع لبعضنا البعض.
Well, my journey kept going on.
حسن، واستمرت رحلتي.
My dad said, "That’s one,"
أبي علّق قائلا ،"هذه هي،"
and I still didn’t let that go.
وأنا لم أفرط في شيء.
I worked for the Coastguard, was made a U.N. Goodwill Ambassador.
عملت لفائدة خفر السواحل، كنت سفير النوايا الحسنة للأمم المتحدة .
I wrote regulations for the United States --
كتبت قوانين للولايات المتحدة --
I mean, I wrote oil spill regulations.
أعني، كتبت قوانين لتسرب النفط.
20 years ago, if someone had said to me,
أعني، لو كان قال لي أحدهم قبل عشرين سنة،
"John, do you really want to make a difference?"
"جون، هل حقا تودّ أن تحدث تغييرا؟"
"Yeah, I want to make a difference."
"أجل، أودّ أن أحدث تغييرا."
He said, "You just start walking east;
قال،" ابدأ بالمشي نحو الشرق،
get out of your car and just start walking east."
ترجّل سيارتك و ابدأ بالمشي نحو الشرق."
And as I walked off a little bit, they'd say, "Yeah, and shut up, too."
ولما مشيت قبالته قليلا، قال،"نعم، عليك أن تصمت، أيضا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"You’re going to make a difference, buddy."
سوف تحدث تغييرا يا صديقي."
How could that be, how could that be?
كيف حصل ذلك، كيف حصل ذلك؟
How could doing such a simple thing like walking and not talking
كيف يمكن لأشياء بسيطة نفعلها مثل المشي و التوقف عن الكلام
make a difference?
أن تحدث تغييرا؟
Well, my time at the Coast Guard was a really good time.
حسن، كانت الأوقات التي أمضيتها في خفر السواحل أوقاتا ممتعة.
And after that -- I only worked one year --
وبعد ذلك -- عملت لسنة واحدة --
I said, "That's enough. One year's enough for me to do that."
قلت،" هذا يكفي، عمل هذا طوال سنة هو كاف."
I got on a sailboat and I sailed down to the Caribbean,
حصلت على مركب شراعي ، وأبحرت وصولا الى منطقة البحر الكاريبي،
and walked through all of the islands, and to Venezuela.
ومررت بكل الجزر وصولا إلى فنزويلا.
And you know, I forgot the most important thing,
وتعلمون، نسيت الأمر الأكثر أهمية،
which is why I started talking, which I have to tell you.
وهو سبب بدئي بالمشي، وهو ما علي أن أقوله لكم.
I started talking because I had studied environment.
بدأت بالمشي لأنّي درست البيئة،
I’d studied environment at this formal level,
لأنّي درست البيئة عند هذا المستوى، هذا المستوى الشكلي،
but there was this informal level.
ولكن كان هناك أيضا هذا المستوى الحقيقي.
And the informal level --
و المستوى الحقيقي --
I learned about people, and what we do and how we are.
درست أحوال الناس، وماذا نفعل وكيف نبدو.
And environment changed from just being about trees and birds
فتغير مفهوم البيئة من مجرد التطرق للأشجار و الطيور
and endangered species to being about how we treated each other.
و الأصناف المهدّدة بالإنقراض إلى كيفية معاملتنا لبعضنا البعض.
Because if we are the environment,
لأنه إذا كنا نحن نمثل البيئة،
then all we need to do is look around us
فإنه علينا جميعا أن ننظر حولنا
and see how we treat ourselves and how we treat each other.
لنرى كيف نعامل أنفسنا و كيف نتعامل مع بعضنا البعض.
And so that’s the message that I had.
وهذه هي الرسالة التي لديّ.
And I said, "Well, I'm going to have to spread that message."
وقلت،"حسن، سوف يكون عليّ نشر هذه الرسالة."
And I got in my sailboat, sailed all the way through the Caribbean --
وركبت مراكبي الشراعي، وأبحرت على طول منطقة البحر الكاريبي --
it wasn't really my sailboat, I kind of worked on that boat --
لم يكن حقا مراكبي الشراعي، لقد عملت على ذلك القارب --
got to Venezuela and I started walking.
ذهبت إلى فنزويلا و بدأت العمل.
This is the last part of this story, because it’s how I got here,
هذا هو الجزء الأخير من الحكاية، لأنه يصف كيف وصلت الى هنا،
because I still didn't ride in motorized vehicles.
لأنني لا أزال أمتنع عن ركوب المركبات الآلية.
I was walking through El Dorado -- it's a prison town, famous prison,
كنت أسير خلال "الإدورادو" -- انه سجن، سجن شهير،
or infamous prison -- in Venezuela, and I don’t know what possessed me,
أو سجن غير معروف -- في فنزويلا ، ولا أدري مالذّي اعتراني،
because this was not like me.
لأنّ هذا لم يكن مثلي.
There I am, walking past the guard gate and the guard stops and says,
وصلت هناك، مررت أمام بوّابة الحرس فاستوقفني الحرس قائلا،
"Pasaporte, pasaporte," and with an M16 pointed at me.
"بَزَبُرْتِي، بَزَبُرْتِي" (جوازك،جوازك) و كانت بندقية م16 موجهة صوبي.
And I looked at him and I said, "Passport, huh?
نظرت إليهم و قلت،" الجواز، هاه،
I don't need to show you my passport. It’s in the back of my pack.
ليست مضطرا لأريكم جوازي، إنه في حقيبتي في الخلف.
I'm Dr. Francis; I'm a U.N. Ambassador and I'm walking around the world."
"أنا الدكتور فرنسيس، أنا سفير لدى الأمم المتّحدة و أنا بصدد التجول حول العالم مشيا.
And I started walking off.
وبدأت بالإبتعاد مشيا.
What possessed me to say this thing?
مالّذي اعتراني حتّى أقول ذلك؟
The road turned into the jungle.
انحرف الطريق نحو الغابة.
I didn’t get shot.
لم يطلقوا النّار عليّ.
And I got to -- I start saying, "Free at last --
توجهت نحو -- جعلت أقول، و قد صرت حرا أخيرا،
thank God Almighty, I’m free at last."
أشكر الله سبحانه وتعالى، أنا أخيرا حرّ.
"What was that about," I’m saying. What was that about?
ماذا كان ذلك، كنت أقول، ماذا كان ذلك؟
It took me 100 miles to figure out that, in my heart, in me,
استغرق منّي الأمر 100 ميل لأكتشف أنه في قلبي، في داخلي،
I had become a prisoner.
أصبحت سجينا.
I was a prisoner and I needed to escape.
أصبحت سجينا و كان عليّ الهروب.
The prison that I was in was the fact that I did not drive
السجن الذي كنت بداخله كان حقيقة أنّي لا أقود
or use motorized vehicles.
و لا أستعمل المركبات الآلية.
Now how could that be?
الآن كيف كان لذلك أن يحدث؟
Because when I started, it seemed very appropriate to me
لأنّني عندما بدأت، كان يبدو لي من المناسب جدا
not to use motorized vehicles.
ألا أستعمل المركبات الآلية.
But the thing that was different
ولكن ما كان مختلفا
was that every birthday, I asked myself about silence,
هو أنّه في كل ذكرى عيد ميلاد، كنت أتسائل عن الصمت،
but I never asked myself about my decision to just use my feet.
ولكنّي لم أسأل نفسي قطّ عن قراري استعمال قدميّ فقط.
I had no idea I was going to become a U.N. Ambassador.
لم أكن أعلم أنّي سوف أصبح سفيرا لدى الأمم المتّحدة.
I had no idea I would have a Ph.D.
لم أكن أعلم أنّني سأحصل على شهادة الدكتورا.
And so I realized that I had a responsibility to more than just me,
لذا أدركت أنني أتحمل أكثر من مسؤولية نفسي،
and that I was going to have to change.
وأنني كنت على وشك أن أتغّير.
You know, we can do it.
تعلمون، يمكننا أن نفعل ذلك.
I was going to have to change.
كنت على وشك أن أتغّير.
And I was afraid to change,
كنت خائفا من التغيير.
because I was so used to the guy who only just walked.
لأنّي كنت شديد الإرتباط بذلك الشخص الّذي يمشي فقط.
I was so used to that person that I didn’t want to stop.
كنت شديد الإرتباط بذلك الشخص الّذي لا يودّ التوقّف.
I didn’t know who I would be if I changed.
لم أكن أدري كيف سأصبح إذا تغيرت.
But I know I needed to.
ولكنّي كنت على يقين أنه عليّ فعل ذلك.
I know I needed to change, because it would be the only way
كنت على يقين أنه عليّ فعل ذلك، لأنه السّبيل الوحيد
that I could be here today.
لأكون بَيْنَكُمْ اليوم
And I know that a lot of times
ولكنّي أعلم أنه و في الكثير من الأوقات
we find ourselves in this wonderful place where we’ve gotten to,
نجد أنفسنا في هذا المكان الرّائع الّذي حصلنا عليه،
but there’s another place for us to go.
ولكن علينا الذّهاب إلى مكان آخر.
And we kind of have to leave behind the security of who we’ve become,
و علينا أن ننحّي جانبا الإحساس بالأمن بذلك الذي نحن عليه،
and go to the place of who we are becoming.
والتَّحَوُّلَ إلى ما سنصير عليه.
And so, I want to encourage you to go to that next place,
لذا أودّ أن أدفعكم للتحوّل إلى المكان الموالي،
to let yourself out of any prison that you might find yourself in,
والنَّأيَ بأنفسكم عن أيِّ سجن يمكن أن تجدوا أنفسكم فيه،
as comfortable as it may be, because we have to do something now.
مهما كانت درجة رفاهيتة، لأنّه يجدر بنا الآن القيام بشيء ما.
We have to change now.
علينا أن نتغيّر فورا.
As our former Vice President said,
وكما قال نائب الرئيس السابق،
we have to become activists.
علينا أن نصبح نشطاء.
So if my voice can touch you,
فإذا كان لصوتي وَقْعٌ عليكم،
if my actions can touch you, if my being here can touch you,
إذا كان لنشاطي وَقْعٌ عليكم، فإذا كان لوجودي هنا وَقْعٌ عليكم،
please let it be.
رجاءا دعوا ذلك يحصل.
And I know that all of you have touched me
و أنا أعلم أنّه كان لِكُلٍّ منكم وقع عليَّ
while I’ve been here.
طوال وجودي هنا.
So, let’s go out into the world
لذا دعونا نخرج للعالم
and take this caring, this love, this respect
ولنصطحب معنا هذه الرعاية، هذا الحبّ، هذا الإحترام
that we’ve shown each other right here at TED,
الذي عاملنا به بعضنا البعض هنا في "تد"
and take this out into the world.
ولنأخذه معنا إلى العالم.
Because we are the environment,
لأنّنا نحن الّذين نمثّل البيئة،
and how we treat each other
وأسلوب تعاملنا مع بعضنا البعض
is really how we’re going to treat the environment.
يعكس تماما كيفيّة تعاملنا مع البيئة.
So I want to thank you for being here
لذا أودّ أن أشكركم لحضوركم هنا
and I want to end this in five seconds of silence.
و أودّ أن أختم بخمس ثوان من الصمت.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)